### PRESTON SPENCER

DATA ANALYST

#### LINKEDIN PROFILE | GITHUB PROFILE

**\** 704-724-5917

**Q** prestonspencer3@gmail.com

Nashville, TN

#### **ABOUT ME**

I am an analytic and logic-driven problem solver and project manager with more than 10 years of experience across public health, hospital operations, and journalism fields. My interest in data analytics and its potential for delivering insights to drive and unlock business growth has led me to learn SQL, Python, and advanced Excel technical skills through Nashville Software School.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of North Carolina - Chapel Hill

Bachelor's Degree, English

**Graduated** 2011

Nashville Software School

Data Analytics Consortium

**Graduating** January 2023

# DATA ANALYTICS TECHNIAL SKILLS

SQL

Python

Excel

Power BI

Tableau

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Program Manager

Vanderbilt University Medical Center Cumberland Pediatric Foundation June 2017 - Present Nashville, TN

- Managed education, research, and group discount programs for Vanderbilt-affiliate nonprofit that supports a network of 75 community-based primary care pediatric clinics and 700 physician members
- Grant writer and manager for projects aimed at improving vaccine rates, antibiotic stewardship, tobacco cessation, suicide prevention, and childhood asthma
- Managed more than \$4 million in grant awards over 5-year period

#### **Business Resource Analyst**

Iredell Health System

Nov 2015 - May 2017 Statesville, NC

- Manager of health system's GPO contract agreements, tasked with financial stewardship of purchasing department for a 247bed hospital with 14 affiliated outpatient clinics
- Identified more than \$1 million-plus in potential annual savings, worked in partnership with clinical leadership to implement more than \$400K of savings over three fiscal years
- Data analysis of purchasing and contract data done with Excel using pivot tables and VLOOKUP

#### **Newspaper Reporter**

July 2011 - Oct 2015 Statesville, NC

Statesville Record & Landmark

- Education and Health reporter for daily newspaper, also regular contributor to public safety, political, business, and non-profit beats
- Reporting heavily focused on the policies and finances of the county's two public school systems

## DATA ANALYTICS PROJECTS

#### Nashville Software School Data Analytics Consortium

July 2022 - January 2023 (Expected Graduation)

- Intensive bootcamp focusing on data analytics fundamentals and problem-solving
- Used real-world datasets, including projects where findings were presented to community stakeholders
- SQL analysis performed with joins, subqueries, CTEs, and window functions
- Built and deployed dashboards using Tableau and Power BI
- Performed exploratory data analysis using Python's pandas library
- Created data visualizations using matplotlib, seaborn, and folium
- Project management/tracking with GitHub
- Analyzed data using Microsoft Excel through pivot tables, lookups, and PowerPivot

#### Datasets Utilized in Projects - Highlights

- Medicare Providers Opioid Prescribing
- TN Dept of Health Early Intervention System
- Nashville Traffic Accidents
- MLB Historical Baseball Statistics
- Worldwide GDP and Internet Usage
- NYC Central Park Squirrel Census
- Antarctica Penguin Research